Guide to the David Karsner Papers on the Bill Haywood Espionage Trial TAM.430
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
David Karsner Papers on the Bill Haywood Espionage Trial
1918-1930
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Karsner, David, 1889-1941
TAM.430
0.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
David Karsner (1889-1941) was a socialist activist, author and newspaperman who served for some years as an editor of the Socialist Party's newspaper, The New York Call. The collection contains correspondence, transcripts and clippings relating primarily to Karsner's coverage of the 1918 trial, The United States of America v. William D. Haywood, et al., held in the District Court of the United States, Northern District of Illinois, Eastern Division in Chicago.
Box 1
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials found in collection; provenance is unknown. The accession number associated with this collectionis 1950.241.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically. The collection is organized into one series:
Missing Title
Series I: Subject Files, 1918-1930.
Historical/Biographical Note
David Fulton Karsner (1889-1941), socialist activist, author and newspaperman, was born in Baltimore, Maryland. Educated at the McDonough School in Baltimore, Karsner began his journalistic career in Chicago by 1907. There he developed an interest in socialism through his association with Upton Sinclair, and became acquainted with Clarence Darrow, Carl Sandburg, Jack London and other notable leftists. In 1911 Karsner relocated East and worked for a number of newspapers, including the New York Tribune, the Philadelphia Ledger and the New York Daily News. He served as Sunday editor and then managing editor of the Socialist Party's newspaper,The New York Call. In 1918, the Call assigned Karsner to cover the trial, United States of America v. William D. Haywood, et al., in which 166 members of the Industrial Workers of the World were charged and convicted of impeding the war effort under the 1917 Espionage Act. The case was tried in the District Court of the United States, Northern District of Illinois, Eastern Division in Chicago.
Karsner married Rose Greenberg, a Romanian-born Socialist with whom he had a daughter, Walta (named for Walt Whitman). After the marriage dissolved, Karsner married Esther Eberson. (Rose would later marry James P. Cannon, the leader of U.S. Trotskyism.)
Karsner wrote numerous biographies, including two volumes on the socialist leader and five-time presidential candidate, Eugene V. Debs, who became a close friend. Karsner collaborated with the aging Debs on his only published book, Walls and Bars, a prison memoir.
When he died of a heart attack at age 51 on February 20, 1941, Karsner was employed as a copyreader on the New York Post.
Among Karsner's works are: Debs: His Authorized Life and Letters from Woodstock Prison to Atlanta (1919); Horace Traubel: His Life and Work (1919); Talks with Debs in Terre Haute (and Letters from Lindlahr) (1922); Sixteen Authors to One (1928); Andrew Jackson: The Gentle Savage (1929);and Silver Dollar: The Story of the Tabors (1932).
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains clippings, correspondence and transcripts relating primarily to Karsner's coverage of the 1918 trial,The United States of America v. William D. Haywood, et al. Notable items include correspondence from William D. "Big Bill" Haywood written while incarcerated in Leavenworth, Kansas, and as a fugitive in the Soviet Union; an original sketch made by Haywood in the courtroom; and Karsner's dispatch to The New York Call describing the emotional courtroom meeting of Haywood and Eugene V. Debs. Correspondents include Roger N. Baldwin of the National Civil Liberties Bureau and A.S. Embree and K.B. McDonald of the General Defense Committee of the Industrial Workers of the World (I.W.W.). Trial transcripts document statements made by defendants prior to sentencing, and clippings relate mostly to the trial and Haywood's subsequent escape to Moscow. The two separated photographs are of George V. Vanderveer, General Counsel for the I.W.W., and Frank K. Nebeker, Chief Prosecutor.
Separated Materials
Two photographs have been separated to the Non-Print Department of the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Archives.
Prisoners -- Correspondence.; Trials (Espionage) -- United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Journalism, Socialist -- United States; Transcripts.; Correspondence.; New York call (New York, N.Y.); Karsner, David, 1889-1941; Embree, A. S.; Baldwin, Roger Nash, 1884-1981; Industrial Workers of the World; Industrial Workers of the World. General Defense Committee; Haywood, Big Bill, 1869-1928
- Series I: Subject Files, 1918-1930.
  - Correspondence, 1918, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Haywood, William D.: Activities in Soviet Union (Clippings), Undated, 1921-1922 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Haywood, William D.: Correspondence, 1918-1919, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Haywood, William D.: Death (Clippings), [1928] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Haywood, William D.: Escape to the Soviet Union (Clippings), 1921 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Haywood, William D.: Sketch of "Miss Evers", 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5a)
  - National Civil Liberties Bureau: Correspondence (Roger N. Baldwin and Albert D. Silver), 1918, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Progressive Farmers and Household Union: Race Riot Trial, Arkansas (Clipping), Oct 3, [1921] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - United States of America v. William D. Haywood, et al.: Amnesty for Industrial Workers of the World (Clippings), Undated, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - United States of America v. William D. Haywood, et al.: Defendants' Exhibit, Marlin Arms Corporaton (Clipping), [1918] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - United States of America v. William D. Haywood, et al.: Original Drawing by Haywood of Tribune Staff Artist, Miss Evers, Apr 2, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - United States of America v. William D. Haywood, et al.: Photographs of George F. Vanderveer, General Counsel for the I.W.W., and Frank K. Nebeker, Chief Prosecutor (Photocopies), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - United States of America v. William D. Haywood, et al.: Telegram Dispatch to The New York Call (Eugene V. Debs Visits Court), Aug 12, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - United States of America v. William D. Haywood, et al.: Transcript of Defendants' Statements, Aug 29, 1918-Aug 30, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 13)